<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd upon the occasion of the Queen's death on the 4th Sunday in Lent, being the 3d of March, 1694/5 / by W. Perse ...</title>
            <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33385</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13286620</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13286620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1039:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd upon the occasion of the Queen's death on the 4th Sunday in Lent, being the 3d of March, 1694/5 / by W. Perse ...</title>
                  <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. White for Robert Clarke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print showthrough with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVI, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:98812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guil. Pearſon,</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto Patri ac D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> 
               <hi>Johanni</hi> Archiepiſc. <hi>Ebor.</hi> à Sacris. Dom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martij,</hi> 11<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98812:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd upon the occaſion OF THE Queen's Death, On the <hi>4th.</hi> Sunday in <hi>Lent;</hi> Being the <hi>3d.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1694/5.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. PERSE,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of <hi>Malton,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>Lewis</hi> Earl of <hi>Feverſham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Dulce eſt Mori cum Plorant Sui.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen: Trag:</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. White,</hi> for <hi>Robert Clarke,</hi> at the Signe of the Crown at the <hi>Minſter-Gate,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98812:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the Lady <hi>Palmes.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN I was once perſwaded to make the enſuing Diſcourſe Publick; I did not in the Leaſt doubt with my Selfe to whom I ought to preſent it. The Place where it was delivered, (as being part of your ancient <hi>Paternall Inheritance</hi> for which you have done ſo much and for which you are ſtill doing more good) the many great Favours I have received from your Ladyſhip, Since my Lot fell in this Soyle; And the Subiect matter of it, Seeme naturally to direct me at what Shrine to Offer it.</p>
            <p>The great Eſteeme you ever had for that miracle of Vertue and Goodneſs, our late moſt Gracious Princeſs Queen Mary, (now of happy, and glorious Memory,) the tender concern you expreſſt for her, during her dangerous, and too fat all Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (according to the account you were pleaſed to give us here in the Country) make me hope that the Offering tho but Small, yet as being well intended, will in ſome meaſure attone for my Preſumption in placeing your Honours Name before it.</p>
            <p>Beſides: your great, and Singular Goodneſs, and Piety; Your extenſive Charity, eminently Shown, not only towards thoſe of your owne Town and Neighbour hood, for whom
<pb facs="tcp:98812:2"/>you and your truly worthy Husband have ſet up a Linnen Manufacture at your great Charge to employ the many Poor among us, and to afford them a Competent Subſiſtence; But alſo your Signall Bounty, and Liberality towards thoſe diſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed Proteſtants who left their Country, Relations, and all that they had for Chriſts and his Goſpells ſake (in both which Remarkeable Inſtances, you did follow the noble, and truly Chriſtian Example of our late Gracious, and never Sufficiently to bee Lamented Princeſs) Challenge this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation as your ſole Right from me who am ſo much indebted to your goodneſs, and Kindneſs, ever Since I had the Honour to be known unto you; which I ſhall ever gratefully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and take this Opportunity, (as being the only Publick one I may ever have) to teſtify the ſame to the World, But ſhall ever in Private Pray for the Happineſs, Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and Proſperity of your Ladyſhip, and moſt worthy, and truly honourable Family both in this world, and that which is to come; as is the Duty of.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Humble, and Obedient Servant,</hi> William Perſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98812:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached on the <hi>3d.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> and the <hi>4th.</hi> Sunday in <hi>Lent;</hi> With Relation to the Queens Death.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>St. <hi>Matthew</hi> 26th. <hi>C. 13, V.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Verily I ſay unto you, Whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the whole World, there ſhall alſo this, that this Woman hath done, be told for a Memoriall of her.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Have made choice of this remarkeable paſſage of Scripture at this time, upon a twofold Occaſion, to both which it ſeemes to be moſt fitly, and properly ſuited: So that if the time be a circumſtance, which like an Embroidred Border, ſetts off the richneſs of a Garment; and if a Word ſpoken in ſeaſon, and duly applyed, be as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> tells us it is, as comely and Ornamental as Apples of Gold incloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Pictures of Silver, then theſe few words of our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who ſpake as never Man ſpake, will receive all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that a due timeing and a Seaſonable opportunity can give them.</p>
            <p>The happy action to which our Saviour referrs; and of which he gives ſo large, and ſo laſting a Commendation; had an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98812:3"/>immediate relation to his own Death and Buriall, which were ſhortly after to enſue: As he himſelf explaines it in the Verſe foregoing my Text; <hi>For in that ſhe hath poured this Ointement upon my head, ſhe did it for my Buriall.</hi> We are now well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the dayes of Mourning, and humiliation for our Sins, Our treacherous Sins, that occaſioned our Bleſſed Lords ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Paſſion; which cauſed thoſe Bitter paines, and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full excruciations both of Body, and mind which he underwent for them: And therefore ought at this time more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to be lamented, and ſorrowed for by us; as being thoſe Traytors which delivered him over to the mercileſs Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and which nay led him to the Croſs: And which will without a true Repentance and hearty ſorrow for them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of all the benefits of thoſe exquiſite, and all meritorious Sufferings that he underwent for us Men, and our Salvation: And what can be more agreeable and ſeaſonable to prepare our hearts for the better, and more exact celebration of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voute Exerciſes of Religion, which the approaching Solemnity, of our great Paſſeover requires of us; then in the inſiſting on ſome of the particulars of <hi>Maryes</hi> moſt worthy and ſignificant Action which our Saviour here ſo honourably commemorates, and which he hath applyed to this very purpoſe; telling us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that the ſound of it ſhould go forth into all Lands where his Name ſhould be known, and his Goſpel publiſht through the whole World.</p>
            <p>This is the Firſt, and greateſt Reaſon of my pitching on this Subject; but I cannot ſay as our Saviour does in anſwer to the Lawyers queſtion; <hi>Which is the great Commandement?</hi> That the Second is like unto it: Though there is great reaſon for that alſo: For the wiſe man hath told us that the <hi>Memory</hi> of <hi>the juſt ſhall be bleſſed:</hi> And his Royall Father <hi>David</hi> hath aſſured us, that <hi>the actions of the Righteous ſhall be had in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Remembrance.</hi> Therefore when I ſhall have ſhown you how proper a preparation that Action of <hi>Marys</hi> was for our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98812:4"/>bleſſed Saviours Buriall, and exhorted all thoſe who deſign to ſolemnize his Death and Paſſion in that holy Sacrament, which he Inſtituted as a perpetuall memoriall of it, to imitate this bleſſed Saint and Convert in that ſignall Act of Love, Charity, and Gratitude which ſhe performed to her Saviour in poureing that precious Oyntment upon his Head. I ſhall then crave your Patience, to preſent a ſmall free-will Offering of the ſweeteſt Oyle I can pour out of my ſhallow and narrow Cruſe, mixt with a few graines of Frankincenſe for a memoriall of another <hi>Mary,</hi> our late moſt gracious Queen, now of Glorious, and happy memory; whoſe Works ſhall ever praiſe her in the Gates, and whoſe remembrance ſhall be like the Perfume made by the Art of the Apothecary; and as ſweet, and Fragrant to all that wiſh well to the Reformed Religion in generall, and to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the moſt refined part of it, and to the happineſs, and Proſperity of theſe Kingdoms; as that precious Oyntment, which this Bleſſed Woman in my Text ſo liberally poured on our Saviour, to anoint him aforehand (as I doe now his Glorious ſervant this day) to his Buriall.</p>
            <p>But Firſt, I am to preſent you with this remarkeable Action, of which our Saviour takes ſo much notice; which though full of Time, and which hath ſeen the end and Flight of many Ages, doth it ſelfe never grow Old: This action ſo long ſince performed, might with many others, which perhaps appear'd more glorious and conſpicuous in the Eyes of Men have been by this time darkely Buried in the Tomb of Oblivion; but that he in whoſe hand Time and Eternity is graſp't, hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that it ſhall ever Grow, and Flouriſh, — <hi>Occulto ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut Arbor aevo,</hi> ſpreading it's branches far and wide over the Face of the whole Earth; deſying all the furious blaſts and Tempeſts that the envy and malice of the Prince of the Air can raiſe to overthrow it: For he in whoſe power, and at whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all Created Beings are, hath Circumſcribed the memorial of it, with no other Limits then the Compaſs, and Duration
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98812:4"/>of the whole World: <hi>Pliny</hi> juſty eſteems them happy who writ things worthy to be read; but prefers them in the degree of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity who acted things worthy to Be written: In what bleſſed Eſtate then muſt they bee who have done ſuch things which the holy Spirit hath thought fit to commend to Poſterity, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter in the never periſhing Volumes of Gods word, and which ſhall bee read, preacht, and publiſht through all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Quarters and Corners of the Earth: of which Sort our Saviour aſſures us this is one: <hi>Verily I ſay unto you Whereſoever this Goſpell, ſhall bee preacht, there ſhall alſo this that this Woman hath done be told for a Memorial of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words contain our Saviours defence, and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Action which to ſome of the Diſciples ſeemed worthy of a ſharp and reproachful Cenſure. Wherein we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe 3 parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Glory and Excellency of the Action: It was thought ſo worthy, and deſerving by our Saviour as not fit to be ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and buried in Oblivion, but to be told and ſpread abroad.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The end of the Publication; <hi>for a Memorial of her:</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others to follow her good example, Praiſe: Credit, and Reputation are great incitements, and Invitations to the promote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vertuous Actions in the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Extent of this glorious Publication. Where ever the Goſpel ſhould be Preacht in the whole World. No good Action whatſoever, ſhall go unregarded or unrewarded: But ſuch Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent acts of Piety, Love, and Gratitude, ſuch as this was, ſhall have an eſpecial Mark, and Star of honour affixt to them: They are <hi>Cedro linends;</hi> they are to be anointed with the Oyl of Cedar, to preſerve them from corruption; Things worthy of Immortality; to be had in everlaſting Remembrance,</p>
            <p>What this Excellent Action was of which our Saviour gives this great Elogy, we find <hi>Verſe</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> of this <hi>Chapter. There came unto him a Woman having an Alabaſter Box of precious Oyntment, and poured it upon his head as he ſate at meat</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98812:5"/>
In which we are to conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Quantity which this good woman preſented, and beſtowed upon Chriſt. It was an Alabaſter Boxe; which when filled with that Ingredent denoted a ſtated Meaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Quality of the Oyntment which ſhe dedicated to Chriſts Service, it was precious Oyntment; Oyntment of Spikenard, pure, and unmixt, a confection of the pureſt nard; and of the choiceſt part of it: the Spike, or Top of it: both for the makeing true, and for the value coſtly: as we may gather from Herodotus, who tells us that Cambyſes King of Perſia ſent an Alabaſter box of Oyntment (the very ſame quantity) as a preſent to the King of <hi>Ethiopia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We are to conſider the two Severall ends at which this Action aimed</p>
            <p n="1">1. The end to which <hi>Mary</hi> deſignd it; which was to give a noble teſtimony of her Love, and gratitude to her Lord, and Maſter, by that honour which ſhe Showed him in pouring that quantity of Precious Oyntment upon him at that great Feaſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ultimate End to which the Divine Providence had orderd it: that is, to be a preparative to our Saviours Death, and Buriall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Quantity: her Preſent was large, as we may gather from the veſſell wherein it was Contained; an Alabaſter Box; which denotes a veſſell of Such an exact Size, and figure wherein thoſe precious Oyntments were preſerved: and relates not ſo much to the matter, as to the forme, and, capacity of it: For Theocritus makes Mention <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his booke of meaſures tells us, that this Alabaſter Box of Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was a pellucid Veſſellof a glaſſy Subſtance, (elſe it could not ſo eaſily breake) containeing a pound: Which exactly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with what St. <hi>John</hi> mentions, <hi>John:</hi> 12 c: <hi>3d</hi> v. And <hi>Mary</hi> took a pound of Oyntment: A very larg proportion, conſidering the ſearceneſs, and the richneſs of the perſume. where the Heart is well affected, there the hand will ſoon Sympathize: where the heart ſtrings are dilated, the fibres of the hand will not bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98812:5"/>contracted. Love ſooner and more infallibly then Night ſhade, makes all Locks and Barrs fly open before it: when once that charming Power hath inſinuated it ſelf into the Breaſt; it diſſolves the before ſtony and unrelenting heart, and in larges the before narrow thoughts and diſpoſitions of the Soul; it thaws the ioye, and cold Temper that was predominant; and makes the waters which were ſluggiſh, bound, and without motion to overflow thoſe ſhallow banks wherein they were formerly confin'd: If we love Chriſt as this bleſſed Convert did, we ſhall be ready to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate her generous Example; and be liberal in the expreſſions of our kindneſs to him, and his poor Members: ſhe had received largely at the hand of God, and ſhe returns according to her abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, plentifully: as Chriſt had ſhown the greatneſs of his Love to her in forgiving: ſo ſhe indeavour'd to expreſſe the largeneſs of hers in giving: and as ſhe had much forgiven, ſo ſhe ſhowed by her Preſent, that ſhe loved much: She gave not by drops, but ſhowr'd it down in ſtreams: And as ſhe had received the unction of the holy one, mention'd in the 1. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> in a plentiful Meaſure from him who had it without Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo ſhe returned of the Oyntment which ſhe had at her great coſt procured, very liberally; and having received freely of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals; ſhe was no niggard of her temporals. 'Tis to no purpoſe to give ſparingly, when we may affor'd thorough Gods bleſſing to ſcatter and pour forth largely: for the Charitable Man gaines by what he parts with; whilſt the Covetous wretch whom God abhorreth looſes even what he ſeems to keep.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As what this devout <hi>Mary</hi> preſented unto Chriſt was large for the quantity, ſo was it moſt excellent, and precious for the Quality. She would not as <hi>David</hi> told <hi>Araunah, Offer unto God of that which coſt her nought;</hi> it was <hi>Precious Oyntment.</hi> The ſame Quantity as I told you was a preſent for a King. And To was he to whom this grateful acknowledgment was made: No leſſe then the King of the whole Earth: And though he ſtand in need of none of our Services, ſeeing <hi>the earth is his and the fulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98812:6"/>yet he kindly receives, and graciouſly accepts what we offer with a willing and chearful heart, even for our ſakes; that he may be provoked to ſcatter his bleſſings more profuſely and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly upon us: And therefore lookes upon his Divine Maieſty to be affronted when we ſhow the ſmallneſs of our reſpect by the meanneſſe of our Oblation; either pinching him in the Meaſure; or which is worſe, giving him of that which is vile and of no eſtimation, for the Nature and Quality of it.</p>
            <p>Indeed a Mite is accepted; but it is where the will is large and the ability ſmall: And this good Woman received our Saviours Praiſe and commendation for this Act, becauſe he expreſſes it in the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>Mark 8th. v.</hi> ſhe did what ſhe could: As ſhe was very rich, and wealthy for her ſubſtance, ſo ſhe ſhow'd the Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of her ſpirit by the Price and value of her donation. From whence we may obſerve: that God accepts us according to what we have, and not according to what we have not: If we have but a Mite, he does not look for a farthing: And if we have ten thouſand Rivers of Oyle, he does not expect to be put off with a cup of cold Water. Tho he is pleaſ'd rather to abate then to exact the whole of us, takeing ſhort of what he might juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of us: Otherwiſe were he exact to mark either what we omit, or wherein we have done amiſſe, who might be able to ſtand before him; but ſtill our Obedience muſt bear ſome Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our knowledge, our Power, and our opportunities of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; when we do what we can, then we do in Gods ſight what we ought; when we do what he by his Grace inables us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; we need not queſtion but thoſe Teſtimonyes of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſhall be graciouſly receivd, as this happy Action of <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> was, when ſhe poured a Pound of precious Oyntment on our Saviours Head: for as ſhe was not niggardly as to the quantity, ſo was ſhe not negligent as to the quality: She would ſerve God of the beſt. <hi>Abels</hi> Offering was accepted, becauſe he took of the choiceſt of his Flock, and of the ſat of it; and <hi>Cains</hi> reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe he brought of the fruits of the ground which firſt came
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98812:6"/>to hand, without picking or culling: And it is to be obſerved, that in all the Commands that God gave concerning Sacrifices or Oblations, he alwayes order'd the beſt, and the choiceſt to be preſented for his Service; nothing that was common, or defective was to appear in his preſence; nothing that had any ſpot or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh was to fall before his Altar: God in ſome Caſes abated of the Meaſure and quantity; if the Offender were not able to bring a Lamb for a ſin Offering, God would accept of two young Turtles, or two young Pidgeons; but we never read that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſ'd with the quality of any Sacrifice: that he either received the halt or the blind.</p>
            <p>But alaſs! How little do we follow theſe Precepts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God? How little do we follow this good Womans Example, in giving the beſt of our ſtore to his uſe and Service? No, rather on the contrary, we are apt not only to pinch him in the Meaſure, which few ſcruple at; but to ſhow our diſreſpect to him likewiſe by ſetting apart that which is moſt vile and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible for the ſacred Portion: But above all how careleſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs are we in offering up the calves of our lips; in the dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacrifice of our Prayer unto God, there be but too many who in this ſenſe offer unto God, of that which coſts them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; no, not the leaſt thought, or conſideration: They pour ſorth it may be whole torrents and ſtreams of words, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a drop of ſenſe or meaning; of Zeal or Devotion. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we cannot be of their minds who think that the bare perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Duty, without ever minding of the manner after which it is performed will ſerve the turn; who think they have ſufficiently anſwered the end, when they have mumbled over ſo many <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> and <hi>ave Maries,</hi> and gone over ſuch a ſet of Prayers, or travelled ſo many miles bare footed to viſit the Shrine of a Saint, or to kiſs ſome holy Relick: But we have not learned ſo to ſerve God; this is to worſhip him by Rote, without either will, affection or underſtanding: No! As thoſe Sacrifices were beſt accepted which were wholly conſumed by fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98812:7"/>of which we have ſome Inſtances in Scripture; ſo we may aſſure our ſelves, that no Sacrifice of Prayer, or thanksgiving will find any acceptance at the hand of God which is not firſt kindled by a Heavenly Zeal, and then aſcends by vertue of that holy Flame to him who preſents it in the golden Cenſer of his own Merits to his Almighty Father. Let us be careful in all our addreſſes unto God, In all our Divine Services to be intent upon what we are about; to be elevated, and raiſed in our Spirits; and how ſhort ſoever our Prayers be, let us indeavour they may be fervent and ſincere; if we offer up but two young Turcks let them not want their wings. <hi>Mary</hi> we ſee was careful in what ſhe preſented unto Chriſt; the ſcent of it perfumed the whole Room, the <hi>Whole houſe:</hi> as <hi>St. John</hi> tells us, <hi>was filled with the Odour of the Oyntment:</hi> And if the Acts of our Love, and Charity to Chriſt, and his Members be as unadulterate, and diffuſive, as hers was, we ſhall not fail of the ſame gracious acceptance that ſhe met with, whil'ſt ſhe went to pay the acknowledgment of her thankful heart to her beloved Lord and Maſter. Which leads me to the firſt end for which this Action was deſigned; that which <hi>Mary</hi> aimed at in anointing our Saviour at this time with her coſtly Oyntment. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To give an ample Teſtimony of her Love, and Gratitude, her kindneſs and reſpect to her Saviour who had done ſo great things for her; that was all ſhe aimed at: She dream'd not then either of his Death, or Burial. The greateſt honour that could be ſhown to Gueſts of the beſt Rank, and Faſhion by the Maſter of the Feaſt, was to perfume them with precious Oyntment; and that this was cuſtomary among the Jews, and Romans, and the Greeks alſo, I might ſhow you, were it either a matter in queſtion, or worth the diſpute: the only thing extraordinary in this, was the Quantity; and the anointing of our Saviours feet, a thing unuſual, even where eaſe, and Luxury did moſt abound: And <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us that <hi>Otho</hi> did firſt teach <hi>Nero</hi> to beſmear his feet with precious Oyntments: But this, as I ſhall ſnow you had a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious ſignification, which neither ſhe nor any of the company
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98812:7"/>were aware of. O bleſſed <hi>Mary!</hi> Sweet was thy Oyntment But Sweeter was thy Love: Gracefull was thy Action, but more gracefull was thy affection: The Scent of the rich Perfume, was quickly gone; but the Sweet Odour, and the fragrant Smell of thy pure, and Sincere Love ſhall bee preſerved in the Sacred Records of the Goſpell, as long as the world endures; and the memory of that precious Oyntment wherewith thou didſt anoint thy Saviours head and feet, ſhall bee more laſting, and incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the oyle of Cedar, the great Preſervative againſt the moth of time;</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though <hi>Maryes</hi> deſigne was only true, and unfeigned Love in this Action, yet as our Saviour intimates the divine Providence had a further reach, and proſpect: <hi>Viz:</hi> That this anointeing which was common both to feſtivalls, and Burialls ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematically preſignifye our Lords approaching Death, and Paſſion: Thus our purpoſes often times unawares to our ſelves, ſerve Gods end and looke farther then wee direct them. This Cuſtome of anointing the Body for the ſunerall, and of ſtrawing it over with rich gummes and Spices among the Jews is made plaine from the laſt Offices that were performed by <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of Arimathea, to the Body of our Saviour after it was taken downe from the Croſſe, and before it was layed in the Sepulchre. At feaſts the head was generally anointed, but when the Body was dreſſt, and prepared for a funerall all parts Shared in the anointeing: And if we looke into the nature, and kind of this particular Oyntment which this good woman poured upon the Head, and wherewith ſhe anointed the feete of our Saviour wee ſhall find that as it was a very fit preſent by reaſon of the richneſs of the ſcent and the greatneſs of the Value, to expreſs her Love, and gratitude, ſo that likewiſe it was very proper and correſpondent to the end to which Gods providence had allotted it: <hi>Viz:</hi> To foreſhowe his Death and Buriall.</p>
            <p>The pure confection of Nard was no dry Oyntment, but moyſt, and fluid: Whence Nonnus calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a dew, or watry
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98812:8"/>Subſtance, and is reckoned among thoſe precious Oyntments, which diſtill out of Canes or Stalks either of their owne accord, or when cut, and bruiſed by others: hence this was called Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, from the Tops of the Plant from which that Odoriferous Liquor iſſued, either naturall; or which it yeelded after it was bruiſed, and wounded; and in both theſe reſpects was proper to repreſent Chriſts death, and Buriall. Thus it foreſhowd that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Balme, his precious bloud, which was Shortly after to flow in ſtreames from all the hollow Veſſells of his body: And as the ſtalks were ſometimes bruiſd before they yeelded that Soveraign Balſame, and as <hi>Mary</hi> brake the Albaſter Veſſell before ſhe poured forth the Oyntment, ſo his Body more white, and pure then any Alabaſter, was bruiſed for our Sinnes; and broken for our tranſgreſſions, and from thence did iſſue forth that noble Iuice, that precious liquor, which not only by the fragrancy of the Smell, (as being a Sacrifice of a Sweet ſmelling <hi>Savour</hi>) makes us acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable unto God, but alſo by its healeing balſamick quality cures all our inward wounds, and heales all our ſinfull diſtempers.</p>
            <p>Well didſt thou O <hi>Mary</hi> to diffuſe thy Oyntment over the bleſſed body of thy Lord and Saviour, the holy Ieſus, to mollify it againſt the then approaching time of his bitter, and diſmall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony in the garden; wherein hee was to ſweat blood out of every pore for thy ſake: well didſt thou to anoint that Sacred Head, the head of the univerſe, which was ſhortly to bee crowned with thornes: well didſt thou to anoint thoſe feet the extremeſt parts which came neareſt to the Earth to which hee deſcended for thy good: thoſe feet which had taken ſo many Sharpe, and painfull journyes for the benefit of mankind; well didſt thou to anoint, and Supple thoſe feet which were to Support his Body in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the heavy Load of his Croſſe, made heavier by our ſins, up that ſteep, and craggy hill, Mount <hi>Calvary:</hi> and which were to drop forth a more generous and Soveraign Juice to heal all our Spiritual Infirmities.</p>
            <p>Alaſs; O Lord thou didſt not need any of theſe, to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98812:8"/>Ceremonies, either liveing, or dead: Thou <hi>like the Roſe of</hi> Sharon <hi>and like the Lilly of the Valley,</hi> (to both which thou art compared) had'ſt, as being free from all the pollutions and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, of our decayed Nature, an innate ſweetneſs in thee, far ſurpaſſing all aromatick perfumes: and as there went a healing vertue out of thy Body, ſo likewiſe we may well imagine that an Odoriferous ſcent muſt needs Tranſpire out of that exactly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd Complexion, and conſtitution: Neither didſt thou need either Spices or Oyntment, to preſerve thy body when dead, and laid in the Grave; for that, as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> hath aſſur'd us could <hi>ſuffer no Corruption,</hi> could admit of no Putrefaction: And yet O bleſſed Jeſus thou waſt pleas'd to permit theſe uſual Offices to be performed to thy ſelf, and kindly to accept of them: To ſhow us that thou doſt allow of neatneſs, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, of the <hi>Oyle of gladneſs,</hi> and of the Wine of rejoycing; and that we may be thy Diſciples without wholly abjureing the uſe of thoſe Creatures, which thou of thy Almighty wiſdome, and Infinite bounty haſt provided for the comfort and refreſhment of mankind; and to ſhow us likewiſe that we may, and ought, to take a decent care of our Bodies after their better part their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Companions have left and forſaken them, ſeeing that which ſhall cre long be crumbled to duſt, ſhall by thy allquickning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit return to itsold forme, and thoſe two old Friends be reunited never to ſuffer a ſecond ſeparation. Thus O Lord, both thy Life and thy Death, both thy Burial, and Reſurrectioun, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumſtance thereunto appertaining, teach us ſome or other good Leſſon, and whil'ſt our Meditations are concerning thee, we cannot fail, of wholeſome Inſtructions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond General part of the Text is the end of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of <hi>Maryes</hi> good work: it was done <hi>for a Memorial of her;</hi> where ever vertue and goodneſs break forth eminently, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily like the Sun in its noone-tide ſtrength, there alwayes remaines the indelible Character of a happy Remembrance: The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of this Woman in my Text is chiefly excellent in theſe two reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98812:9"/>
1. It is ſuch a praiſe as ſhall never be in any danger to be loſt, it points to futurity; it ſhall be told in Ages to come: <hi>Praiſe not any</hi> ſaith the wiſe man <hi>before his death;</hi> becauſe ſuch commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations are neither ſafe on his part that commendeth; in that it begetteth a ſhrewd ſuſpition of Flattery; nor on his part that is commended; becauſe if he conceive the praiſe that is ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad of him to be true, it is much to be fear'd that it may puffe him up with Pride, and vain Glory, ſo that the moſt opportune time to give Vertue her deſerved commendations, is when a man can neither be hurt with Flattery, nor infected with Oſtentation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Praiſe that is given of her, is a true, and real Praiſe, ſetled upon a ſolid foundation; ſhe is not much extolled for the Ornaments and good qualities belonging to the Body, as Beauty, comelineſs, and the like, which ſhe had in great Perfection; all which are common to the bad as well as to the good; but ſhe is magnifyed for the Graces of her Mind, for her vertuous and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Works, and is the only Praiſe that <hi>Solomon</hi> admitteth in a Woman: <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her Workes praiſe her in the gates;</hi> with which he concludes his Proverbs, and I the ſecond General, and proceed to the laſt, which I can barely mention.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have here the extent of this manifeſtation of <hi>Maryes</hi> Praiſe: It ſhall reach as far, as the ſound of the Goſpel ſhall be heard; and that is from one end of the Earth to the other. And this had I leiſure to proſecute it, would yeild much matter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our conſideration; I will give you in a little to underſtand how much might be ſaid of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It teaches us that the praiſe of the Juſt is of a certain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and continuance, in reſpect of him from whom it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; for it is not founded upon the Judgment of Man, who often judgeth things to be Praiſe worthy according to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, which oftentimes have no real and intrinſick worth, and value in them. But this is grounded upon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98812:9"/>Judgment of God, who neither is, nor can be capable either of Ignorance, or Error <hi>I ſay unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge not</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 Ep: to the <hi>Cor:</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> at the <hi>5th v. before the time; untill he come that ſhall bring to light the things that are done in darkneſs, and manifeſt the Counſels of the heart, and then every one ſhall have Praiſe of God:</hi> 'Tis Chriſt who gave this Teſtimony of this Woman, whoſe word is more firm, and aſſured then the Poles and Baſis of Heaven, and Earth, for <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away but his word ſhall not paſs away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhowes that the Extent is univerſal: for the Goſpel is a Meſſage of glad Tidings that is to be communicated to all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: It is not ſent into the World to be concealed, or kept cloſe; not to be mutter'd in an unknown Tongue: <hi>No Man lighteth a Candle to put it under a Buſhel;</hi> the light of the word is not to be ſhut up in a dark Lanthorn; nor is the Goſpel given unto Men, that with that unfaithful Servant they ſhould hide it in the Earth; nor is it to be kept in the heart only; Miſtake me not; God grant that it may take deep root there, and that the fruits of it may appear in our Lives, and Converſations; my meaning is this: All thoſe to whom God hath been pleas'd to reveal the Myſtery of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, are bound when lawfully call'd, and Authoriz'd thereunto, to Preach and divulge it unto others, yea a woe is denounced againſt all ſuch as do it not: Though it may be thought fooliſhneſs in ſome who would be thought to be carnally wiſe; yet <hi>it hath pleaſed God by ſuch foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs to make them that believe, truly wiſe unto Salvation:</hi> Let men therefore Reverence the Lords diſpenſation, and be glad to accept of Salvation, upon ſuch termes, and by ſuch means as he hath appointed.</p>
            <p>Thus have I at length finiſht my obſervations upon the main deſign of the Text, ſo farr forth as the time allotted for this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe would give me leave, and in ſome meaſure anſwered one End in pitching upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98812:10"/>
Suffer me now therefore in the ſecond place, which both my Duty and inclination lead me to; to pour a little ſweet Oyl, and to preſent a few drops, (not of what is Precious, for ſuch have I none,) but of the beſt that I have, of that which is true, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere; as preparatory to the Solemn Exequies of our moſt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, and moſt Vertuous Princeſs ſuddenly to be celebrated and perform'd. Another <hi>Mary,</hi> our late gracious Queen, whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ſhall be preſerved freſh, and ſweet in the laſting Records of Fame, ſo long as Vertue, Piety, Charity, Meekneſs, Humility, Wiſdome and all that chain of Graces that added luſtre to her Royal Quality ſhall find any reſpect or Countenance in the World: And truly if ever a larger Tribute of tears then ordinary were due; if ever a more then uſual Portion of ſorrow were allowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; it is certainly at this time for the great, and never enough to be lamented Loſſe of that moſt excellent Priuceſs, who as ſhe was the Glory of this Age, ſo ſhall ſhe be the wonder and Admiration of the next. To ſay nothing of the infinite, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable Loſſe ſuſtained by her right Valiant, and truly kind Lord, the ſole partner of her Affection, as well as Power; whoſe mutual indearments were as much above the ordinary level as their Sacred Perſons were. To ſay nothing of the ineſtimable Damage that the Nation in general feels for want of ſuch a main and ſtrengthning Pillar for the ſupport both of Church and State, we cannot but paſſionately mourn, and lament the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and untimely end of her ſtill blowing, ever growing Vertues; which even in their early Spring yielded ſuch a Sweet, &amp; Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Scent, (like the precious Oyntment in my Text that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed the whole Room) as comforted, and refreſht all that had the happineſs to bee near her.</p>
            <p>My intention is not, as an Herald to proclaime her great Quality, the royall ſtemme from which ſhe was deſcended, nor to ſet forth the worthineſs of that ancient, and Illuſtrious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> the Support of the Proteſtant Religion, in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98812:10"/>Low Countries for the Laſt Ages; into which ſhe was ſo happily married: But give me leave, ut <hi>Proeco Evangelicus,</hi> as an Herald of the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt to blazon Some few of thoſe many vertuous, and moſt excellent qualities for which ſhe was, and ever ſhall be eminent; and which ſhall allways be told for a memorial of her. Theſe are the moſt fragrant flowers that can bee ſtrewne upon her herſe, the richeſt Spices, the ſweeteſt Gums, the moſt precious Oyntments wherewith her honourable Name can bee embalmd.</p>
            <p>Her Exemplary Piety, and Devotion juſtly challenge the firſt place; for as that was allways payed firſt by her unto her God, ſo ought it firſt to bee remembred by us: How frequent, yea how conſtant was ſhee in her private Addreſſes to the Throne of Grace: Her Cloſet, that little Oratory was allways filld with the ſweet Incenſe of fervent, and well directed Prayer: There was no ceaſeing of that holy Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from her Altar: Shee preferred that with-draweing Roome before her own Preſence Chamber; as that beloved place where ſhe could enjoy a more raviſhing delight, and Satisfaction then in all the pompous Ceremonies of her own Splendid, and magnificent Court: where at higheſt ſhe could converſe but with Princes, who though they are called Gods, muſt, (which alaſs ſhe her ſelfe hath too Soon for us, experimented) dye Like men; But in her own retir'd apartment ſhe could pay her homage to the King of Kings, to her Saviour, to her Redeemer: Here it was that ſhe ſo often mourned like a diſconſolate Turtle the Abſence of her deare Conſort whilſt he was expoſeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to all the hazards of warr, to all perills both at ſea and Land for our ſakes; Here ſhe put up her conſtant, and ardent prayers, here ſhe Sent up her moſt fervent Wiſhes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98812:11"/>for his ſafety, his ſucceſs, and his happy Return; And queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs if the Prayers of the faithful are available as to be ſure they are; we are not a little beholden to her devout Oriſons, which we may be ſure were offer'd up with a Fervent, Zealous Spirit, fill'd with pure and unfeigned Love, for thoſe many wonderful deliverances of our moſt Gracious Prince, whoſe Perſon, and affaires ſhe ſo earneſtly, and ſo conſtantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the Divine Protection: Neither is it a ſmall loſſe that the King and the Nation ſuſtain, in the now miſſing the benefies of thoſe winged Meſſengers, which ſhe ſo often ſent up to Heaven to implore its aſſiſtance for his, and our ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Preſervation: But ſure if there be any knowledge in Bleſſed Spirits departed hence, of what is done and tranſacted here below; (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) if there be any ſence remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of humane Affaires, ſhe does not fail to put up her moſt fervent wiſhes for her dear Lords Proſperity, and ſucceſs in all his hazardous undertakings: ſhe does not fail to caſt a kind, and Pitying look upon theſe poor Nations, now depriv'd of her cheerful Prefence, whoſe Intereſt ſhe did ſo Zealouſly eſpouſe: Neither was ſhe leſſe conſtant at the Publick Service of the Church, in her Chappel Royal which ſhe as often as convenient Opportunity would give her leave, graced with her Preſence: Never was the true Reformed Religion, and the pious and Learned Miniſters of it more countenanc'd, and incourag'd, ſince our moſt renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time (of whom in many things ſhe was a lively Pattern) then in her dayes: So that the Church as well as State have loſt in her, their great Patroneſs and protectreſs.</p>
            <p>Thus did Our Gracious Queen <hi>Mary</hi> like the <hi>Mary</hi> in my Text anoint the Head of Chriſt with her precious Oyntment; the Church whereof <hi>Chriſt is Head;</hi> neither was ſhe want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the other part of that Vertuous Womans Action; for ſhe like her, anointed our Saviours feet alſo: The Poor, the loweſt, and extremeſt of his Members, and which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98812:11"/>were moſt ſubject to cold as being fart diſtant from the chief Seat of life, felt the warm Inffuence of her diffuſive Charity in a Princely manner, and an abundant Meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending upon them for their nouriſhment and refreſhment: The <hi>Poor which ſhe had allwayes with her.</hi> The Poor which were her continual care and Charge, taſted liberally of her Royal Bounty: Her Munificent hand, to thoſe who ſtood in need of her aſſiſtance, was like <hi>Mary</hi> to our Saviour, (and what is done to them he lookes upon as done unto himſelf;) no leſſe than a whole Pound of <hi>Precious Oyntment:</hi> her Charity, and liberality to them was of the largeſt Size, and dimenſions; contain'd (if it had any bounds) in the biggeſt <hi>Meaſures, heap'd up, preſſed down and running over:</hi> Theſe are the Innocent Cauſers of our great, and unſpeakeable Loſſe by her ſo ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Removal hence: Theſe were the Importunate Beads-men who have ſollicited Heaven ſo earneſtly for her; who have prayed her up out of a troubleſome World, to Heaven, too ſoon for us, though not for her ſelf.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt her unparallell'd Clemency, that truly Royal Vertue, for which ſhe was ſo Eminent, and which ſo many who ſo little deſerv'd it experimented, be forgotten; how unconcernedly did this Noble hearted, and undaunted Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, at a time when her dear Lord was abſent, and when all things did not anſwer our hopes, and expectations (as the Events of War are various) bear the rude Behaviour, and as bad Language of ſome Inſolent, and diſaffected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which ſhe paſſ'd by with a generous diſdain; puniſhing them moſt nobly, and Chriſtianly, and withal ſeverely by taking no Notice of them. This is that Heavenly Vertue that ſhin'd ſo bright in this adorable Princeſs; and was one of the Beauties of her large, and well complexion'd Soul; which could forgive almoſt as much, and as eaſily as others could offend: This was that Princely Quality which made her not an Angel, but as one of the beſt of thoſe Gods
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98812:12"/>who have the ſubordinate Government of the World under their Supreme and Univerſal Head
<q>Nam cum vincamur in omni Munere, Sola Deos aequat Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nobis.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis this Noble Vertue that transforms our Nature, and makes it in ſome degree like unto him who is <hi>tender hearted, compaſſionate, of great kindneſs repenting him of the evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not meddle with her Political capacity, as being beyond my Sphere; though upon the obſervation of thoſe who tooke notice of the poſture of Publick affaires, during the time of her Adminiſtration; when upon unavoidable Nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſityes; the Husband, and Wife, likeas of Old, the two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Caſtor,</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> ruled by turns when one roſe, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet; have agreed, that in the moſtdifficult Occurrences, She manag'd all things with that Prudence, Conduct, and Courage; as if the Brave, undaunted, Heroick Soul, of the only Partner of her Throne, and Bed had acted in her, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they were both one.</p>
            <p>Her affability, Candor, Humility, and unſullied Innocence, her ſweet, and inoffenſive deportment, and that Noble train of graces already mention'd, that conſtantly attended her, as they gained her the eſteem and veneration of all that knew her, ſo they fitted and qualified her for that bleſſed Compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, with whom ſhe now converſes, ſo that ſhe ſcarce needed any Change, for her Admiſſion into that Heavenly Society. Her ſtay'd, and ſolid Temper of ſpirit muſt, (not without praiſe) be remembred; a temper not to be alter'd by all the ſeveral divertiſements, and avocations, which the high and publick Orb ſhe mov'd in muſt neceſſarily expoſe her to: She uſ'd this World, though living in the greateſt Splendor, and Glory of it, as if ſhe uſ'd it not; as knowing that the faſhion of it muſt, as ſhe her ſelf hath now done, paſſe away; receiving the innocent ſatisfactions without the Vanities, and Impertinencies of it: Like the Famous River <hi>Arethuſa</hi> that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98812:12"/>runs through a large Sea without mixing her pure Waters with that ſalt, and troubled Element, ſhe converſed with her Court, the beſt of which cannot but be tainted with ſome blemiſhes, without partakeing of the Corruptions of it.</p>
            <p>Thus by well ordering and diſpoſeing of her time, ſhe lived much though ſhe Lived not Long: Like a Chymicall Spirit whoſe quantity is Small, but its Vertue and operation great, ſhe had crowded a great heap of life into a narrow compaſſe: not like the many of the world, who can give no other Teſtimony that they Live, but that they breath, and that Scarce wholoſomely too; the greateſt Signe of whoſe Life is their motion, and that generally a very irregular one too. But ſhe, a true <hi>Mary,</hi> whilſt others <hi>cumbred</hi> themſelves about the gay and unneceſſary Vanities of the world, <hi>minded the one thing neceſſary which ſhall never be taken from her:</hi> for her good workes like the Oyntment which that bleſſed Convert poured on our Saviours head ſhall perfume her glorious memory, and make it Smell Sweet in every place where her Sacred Name is mentioned as Long as the world endures: Theſe good workes, and vertuous qualities are the Orators, Eloquent without fiattery, which give her a laſting and never dying Encomium; the loud tongu'd Speakers that have commended her even without a figure, to the very Heavens?</p>
            <p>And now perhaps you may think that by my long inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a few of thoſe many particulars I might have named, that I have been indeavouring to raiſe your Paſſions to an unallowable height, and to Leave Such firm impreſſions of our unutterable loſſe upon your memorys, as will not eaſily be worn out: And truly the parting with ſo much vertue, and Goodneſſe as ſhe was Owner of, eſpecially when it is a Treaſure in this degenerate Age not commonly to be found,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98812:13"/>cannot enough be lamented: But my deſign is more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; Tis to raiſe in you, after her Example an undervalue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe little gay Vanities wherewith the generality of mankind are ſo much infatuated, and to beget in you a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous imitation of thoſe many moſt excellent Qualities for which this bleſſed Saint, and moſt renowned Princeſſe is, and ever ſhall be deſervedly famous.</p>
            <q>I have but one thing more to add.</q>
            <p>I told you the Poor, the many poor whom ſhe fed, and whoſe neceſſities ſhe relieved, were by their continual Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Heaven for her, the Innocent Cauſers of her ſo ſpeedy, and ſudden removal out of a wicked, and deceitful World into the Regions of Everlaſting Peace and Happineſs; Let me put you in mind now what have been the guilty Inſtruments which have pull'd down this fatal calamity on our heads, and deprived us of that great and ineſtimable Bleſſing which we ſo lately enjoy'd; that ſo we may ſeriouſly mourn, and lament for thoſe unhappy Cauſes that have occaſion'd all this trouble and Miſchief unto us; for God <hi>does not afflict willingly, nor grieve the Children of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are our Sins our Crying and hainous Sins of all ſorts, and amongſt the reſt our horrible Ingratitude for the many deliverances which God hath ſent us by the miraculous hand of his over ruling Providence, that have cauſed God <hi>to take away the deſire of our Eyes,</hi> and the Joy of our hearts <hi>With a ſtroke.</hi> 'Tis Sin, which like a Mell-dew, (properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led being ſeemingly ſweet, but really pernicious) hath ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our early hopes, and blaſted our moſt forward Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in a moment. It was Sin that wrought the firſt diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Nature, and brought the <hi>whole Creature into Bondage, from which it longs, and groans to be delivered.</hi> Endleſs it would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98812:13"/>be to ſhow how this helliſh Enchantment hath removed the mighty Kingdomes, and Empires of the Earth; toſſing them like a Ball when they came to her hand, to be under her Dominion, from one to another; from the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> to the <hi>Perſian,</hi> from the <hi>Perſian</hi> to the <hi>Graecian,</hi> from the <hi>Graecian</hi> to the <hi>Roman;</hi> with whom by reaſon of Temperance, frugality, Juſtice and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Honeſty which then reigned amongſt them, the Seat of Majeſty continued for a long Period of Time; till Foreign Conqueſts introduceing exotic Vices, and <hi>Orontes</hi> pouring forth its wanton and Laſcivious ſtreames into the before cold and chaſt <hi>Tiber,</hi> ſhe by degrees receiv'd the fatal Infection, and dyed at laſt of a Luxurious Surfeit. What turns and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of Government; what dire effuſion of Chriſtian Blood, what Ruin, and havock, this too ſucceſsful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Hell hath made in all Places whereever ſhe came; is too diſmal a Story, (but might befit this ſad occaſion) to remember: No wonder then that we who have drunk ſo largely of the inchanted Cup, ſhould feel the miſerable effects of it, and that we who have been intoxicated with the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching Potion, ſhould partake of the ſhamefull Spueing: Let us therefore whilſt the ſtroke of Gods hand is freſh upon us truly bewayl our manifold Sins that have put our hopes ſo far backward, and that have already coſt us ſo dear, and amend our lives leſt a worſe thing befal us. God miraculouſly delivered the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from their <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage but when they murmured againſt their Deliverer and were diſobedient, and continually repining, they provoked him to ſwear in his wrath, that none of them ſhould enter into the Land of Promiſe: He could have led them to <hi>Canaan</hi> by a ſar nearer way; but for their ungrateful carriage toward him, for their hard heartedneſs and unbelief, he haraſſ't them out in the Wilderneſs, till all but <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> of that vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> were conſumed. Let us take heed leſt for our ingratitude, and rebellious diſſatisfied Temper we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98812:14"/>provoke God to put a ſtop to that happy deliverance he hath ſo graciouſly begun among us; and reſerve the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it for another Generation that will be mote thankful then we have been, and will bring forth better fruit; then we have done; Leſt for our unworthy behaviour towards him, and his Laws, he let us only have a <hi>Piſgah</hi> ſight of this <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and never let us enter into an actual poſſeſſion of that happy ſtate of Reſt and Peace of which we have had ſo fair a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Into which State of everlaſting Reſt, and Bliſs, of which <hi>Canaan</hi> was only a Type, the Lord of his Mercy bring us all, under the Conduct of our moſt holy Jeſus, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our Salvation who hath purchas'd it for us with the Price of his own moſt precious bloud: To whom with the Father and holy Spirit be all honour and Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98812:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
